<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The yonger brother his apology by it selfe. Or A fathers free power disputed for the disposition of his lands, or other his fortunes to his sonne, sonnes, or any one of them: as right reason, the laws of God and nature, the ciuill, canon, and municipall lawes of this kingdome do command. By I. Ap-Robert Gent.</title>
            <author>J. A. (John Ap Robert)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 715</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115725</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850943</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850943</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16185</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20768)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1616:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The yonger brother his apology by it selfe. Or A fathers free power disputed for the disposition of his lands, or other his fortunes to his sonne, sonnes, or any one of them: as right reason, the laws of God and nature, the ciuill, canon, and municipall lawes of this kingdome do command. By I. Ap-Robert Gent.</title>
                  <author>J. A. (John Ap Robert)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted, Anno M. DC. XVIII [1618]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I. Ap-Robert = John Ap Robert.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The younger brothers apology.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inheritance and succession --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16185:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16185:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE YONGER BROTHER HIS APOLOGY BY IT SELFE.</p>
            <p>OR A Fathers free power diſputed, for the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his lands, or other his fortunes to his Sonne, Sonnes, or any one of them: as right reaſon, the Laws of God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Ciuill, Canon, and Municipall lawes of this Kingdome do command.</p>
            <p>By I. Ap-Robert Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Niſi Dominus aedificauerit domum: in vanum labora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt, qui aedificant eam.</p>
               <bibl>Pſal. 126.</bibl>
               <p>Vnleſſe our Lord build the houſe: they haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in vayne that build it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted, Anno M. DC. XVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16185:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16185:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO ALL FATHERS AND SONNES OF WORTHY FAMILIES,</hi> VVhome Vertue, Birth, and Learning haue iuſtly ſtiled Gentlemen: Health, Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Increaſe of the beſt Knowledge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the front of this briefe Diſcourſe, there is (Right Worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) already deliuered vnto you ſome light of that which concerneth the Quality, Reaſon, and Scope of the ſame: ſo do I heere ſincerely profeſſe, that I did not priuately write it at firſt but for priuate
<pb facs="tcp:16185:3"/>ſatisfaction; neither do I now make it publique, but with due relation to the generall good of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> and for the exerciſe of Honourable Spirits, in this our much-ſpeaking, &amp; Paradoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Age.</p>
            <p>Not vpon the leaſt preſumption of a ſelf-ſufficiency, to confront there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any receiued Cuſtome (if any ſuch bee) nor to diminish the naturall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, due by Younger Brothers to their Elder; not to enkindle emulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in families; nor to innouate any thing to the preuidice of publique; or priuate quiet (which none I hope wilbe ſo ill affected as to ſuppoſe;) neither myne inoffenſiue zeale for younger brothers (among whom I am rancked one;) nor the abſolute conſent of Imperiall and Eccleſiaſticall Laws (which I hauing a little ſtudied, do not a little reſpect;) nor the particuler honour I beare to the vſages, in this point, of our ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Britans (from whom I am deſcended;) nor diſire to maintaine and iuſtify an
<pb facs="tcp:16185:3"/>act in this Kind, done by a Friend, (whom I muſt euer reuerence;) nor yet the hope of bettering my priuate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes (which mooues men much in theſe our tymes) hath drawne me to this vndertaking: but principally (as before is ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what touched) the ſinguler Reſpect which (as a <hi>Patriote</hi>) I beare to the glory, and good of Gentlemens Houſes, whoſe beſt Originalls, ſureſt means of Maintenance, and principal Ornaments are Vertue, or Force of mynd: The want whereof, is a comon cauſe of ruine.</p>
            <p>The free Power therefore of You who are Fathers, is heere in ſome ſpecial caſes argued and defended, to giue you occaſion therby to conſider with the cleerer eye-ſight, for the eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and continuance of families. Heere alſo the Naturall rights of vs that are children, be ſo diſcourſed and diſcuſſed, as that we younger Brothers may haue cauſe and courage, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour by vertuous means, to make our
<pb facs="tcp:16185:4"/>ſelues (without the leaſt wrong to any) capable (if need ſhalbe) of the chiefeſt vſes. And both, and all are ſo handled, as that no offence can reaſonably ariſe in any reſpect: much leſſe for that the whole is conceiued, and written in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only of an Eſſay or Probleme, to which I bynd no man to affoard more beliefe, then himſelfe hath liking of, &amp; is free to refute the whole, or any part at his pleaſure, as he feeles himſelf able and diſpoſed.</p>
            <p>If I may ſeeme among ſome, to haue handled this ſubiect with more earneſtneſſe and acrimony then they think expedient: let them be pleaſed to weigh the <hi>Decorum</hi> of Diſputes, which is principally herein obſerued their Nature abſolutly requiring quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes, and vehemency on whether ſyde ſoeuer. Neither let this length of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſeeme vnto you like the gates of <hi>Myndus,</hi> which were ſo great and the Citty ſo little, that they miniſtred oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the <hi>Cynick</hi> to ſcoffe at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion,
<pb facs="tcp:16185:4"/>bidding the Townſemen shut their Gates, for feare the Citty should run out through them, ſeeing that in a new Matter a neceſſity lyeth vpon me to vſe ſo large a Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>As for the remedies of Euils, by way of enacting Lawes, that is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per office of Magiſtrates, and Courts of publick Counſell: neuertheleſſe to ſpeak and treat of them (vnder the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and correction of Superiours, to whome I do alwaies very dutifully ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) is a thing which may well belong to euery man. But as for thoſe graue, and learned Cenſors, vnto whom I may ſeeme to haue beſtowed my pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in very needleſſe arguments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no leſſe then I my ſelf, they hould the caſe (as heere it is put) to be moſt cleere, and out of Controuerſy: to ſuch I anſwere, that I wrote it not for them, vnleſſe perhaps to confirme their iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gments; but for others, who are not altogeather ſo perſwaded. Nor to any,
<pb facs="tcp:16185:5"/>as to preſcribe, or bynd further then their owne Conſciences shall thinke good. For that were far too peremto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>Finally, nothing being heer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended but by Authority, Reaſon, and Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, nor any perſon taxed, nor par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler perſonall vices; if neuertheleſſe I haue not performed my part in the worke ſo well as I deſyre, or as the Cauſe deſerues (which I feare I haue not:) yet my hope is (Right Worthy Fathers, and Worthy Sonnes of Right Worthy Families) that for my honeſt meaning, and good intentions ſake, your will euer conceiue well of, and taken into your ſpeciall protection,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your vnfayned vvel-vvisher, I. Ap-Robert.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16185:5"/>
            <head>THE YOVNGER BROTHERS APOLOGIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Occaſion of writing this Apology, is to proue, that Fathers may in ſome caſes diſpoſe of their worldly Eſtates to which of their Sonnes shal reaſonably pleaſe &amp;c. for ſo much therof as they will; and that to be Lawfull by the Law of God, of Nature, and of Nations.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT many moneths ſince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inuited by a deare friend of myne to a ſolemne Feaſt, made by him to many of his well-deſeruing friends, it was my fortune at that Meeting to acquaint myſelfe with many gentlemen of no meane diſcourſe: Whereby I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16185:6"/>feaſted as well my vnderſtanding with their pleaſant ſociety, as my taſte with the variety of moſt excellent meates. With what our Senſes were delighted, I let paſſe to recoumpt, ſince neither profit, pleaſure, nor praiſe can ariſe thereof, either to the writer or reader. Only my intent is, to make my Reader acquainted what accident cauſed me to write this ſmall Treatiſe, and imbouldned me to publiſh the ſame to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon view of this al-reprehending age. In which neuertheles I do rather hope for allowance, then in any ſort to feare diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>For though my ſubiect be new, yet I hope it ſhal want at the firſt rather age &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, which growes by yeares, then probable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yea forcible reaſons to defend it ſelfe. As for friends, I hope it will fynd ſome; and peraduenture more then enemyes, if it deſerue well. For, as younger Brothers be more in number then elder, ſo are they generallie more free in beſtowing their deſerued loue. For want breeding vnderſtanding, makes them knowe &amp; prize their friends according to their worth. Whereas the elder, either ſeated in their Fathers wealth and poſſeſſions, with more then hopes to enioy their Fortunes, do ſomtynes neyther loue truely themſelues, not any man els; but abuſing that which indeed might gaine the loue of God and Man, and eaſily mayntaine their hereditary honour, looſe themſelues in Vanity, &amp; moſt idle courſes; yea, in their Fathers liues,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16185:6"/>ſo ſtrangely carry themſelues as though the law of God, of Nature, and all other Canon, Ciuil, &amp; National lawes, conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; cuſtomesſpru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, could not either in reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bar them of that which they expect; or giue to a wel-deſeruing younger Brother any little hope lawfully to share with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leaſt part of their Fathers inheritance; much leſſe to expect an el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brothers fortunes; oron any termes, or for any cauſe by a Fathers fauour, to ſtep before them.</p>
               <p>Which argument among many others, was then handled by the Company <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Contra,</hi> ſo doubtfully, that it gaue vnto me an occaſion to write this preſent diſcourſe, concerning the free power of ſome Fathers. Wherein I intend to diſpleaſe no elder Brothers; no, not them, who not inheriting their Fathers Vertues, ſtriue not to mayntaine their Anceſtors honour, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing their Noble Names, and Families; by which, as a reward to their vertues and trauells, men haue alwates laboured to liue to al ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages their Poſterity.</p>
               <p>But my intent is to ſhew, how opinion &amp; inconſideration makes oftentimes the wiſe to be ſcrupulous, and through ſuperſtitious zeale, not only to feare to doe that which reaſon may, or might haue comaunded; but raſhly to condemne other mens acts as vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and irreligious. Which according to reaſon and Religion haue bene done &amp; ratified; vſing themſelues that Cuſtome for the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16185:7"/>throw of their families, which was indeed only deuiſed for their preſeruation; and being hood winked with falſe conceipts, do wittingly leaue that, which they and their Anceſtours had gotten, as the reward in this life of their vertues, to be the future fuell of al inordinate deſyres, &amp; Beaſtiall ſenſuality, which in their prouidence they could willingly otherwiſe haue diſpoſed of.</p>
               <p>All which I doubt not but to make cleere to the impartiall reader: prouing by the lawe of God and Man, that a Fathers freedome is ſuch that he may Lawfully, and Religiouſly, giue his lands and goods, or other his fortunes to any of his Children, for the Preſeruation of his Name, and Comfort of his Poſterity, without all ſcruple, as right reaſon, or the better deſerts of a Sonne shall perſwade him, voyd of all ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, or blyndneſſe of affection, which oftentymes leads a Fathers will, and corrupts his vnderſtanding: ſo as he be true Lord therof, not tyed by conſideration of Money receiued, or Contract made by Marriage of his Sonne, which may alter the Caſe, and make the Sonne Lord, and the Father to haue but the vſe only during his life, as all our Common Lawyers well know. In which Caſe, we alſo haue expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that our Law permits many tymes to alter the Title, and to vndoe what by former tymes was held not to be controlled. But of this point I wil not treate. Only I meane to argue, whether a Father poſſeſſed in fee-tayle, may in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16185:7"/>law and equity, vpon the former conſiderations, make any child which he hath, his Heyre, leauing to the reſt a competency; &amp; do an act, which according to equity and Religion may ſtand good and valuable.</p>
               <p>In this my preſent diſcourſe let not any expect many quotations of authors; for I neuer read any of this ſubiect. What I bare away of the diſcourſe made by my friends, that I will ſet downe: and what other reaſons my vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhal affoard, which I hope shal proue ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratiue, that they ſhalbe of Authority ſufficient to ſatisfy my reader, or incite ſome better pen and vnderſtanding, to treat of the ſame more largely &amp; ſubſtantially. And laſtly &amp; cheifly, to cleare ſome of my Worthy friends fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe imputations, which I fynd the ignorant to lay vpon them: which if I may do, I ſhall think my tyme and paines well imployed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16185:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That the grounds of all good Conſtitutions being in Nature; yet shee, neither before, nor after the law of Propriety eſtablished did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund, that all should be left to any one, more then to another.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCH are the wiſe &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate workes of Nature, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is done by her raſhly, or unaduiſedly. For though in the infancy of the world, ſhe had an inuincible power to produce all effects, which thé had their Originall in her: yet being ſtudious to pleaſe mankynd, not only with variety, but alſo with rarity, ſucceſſiuely diſcouereth, and dayly doth diſcloſe to the ſearching wits of the world her ſecrets: as Tyme and Place either hath, or doth dayly beget Occaſion; ſtill as it were keping in ſtore her heauenly treaſure, till mans neceſſity beſt moues her liberality.</p>
               <p>For what can the wit of man deuiſe, or what doth tyme, or Art make knowne, which good is; that Nature, from the firſt tyme ſhee began to work, had not in her (though to her ſelfe only knowne) the ground thereof, either
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16185:8"/>to produce the particuler or general effect which wiſely ſhe left to be tempered according as the reaſon of man (whoſe glory ſhe pretends) ſhould think fitteſt to giue the forme; as tyme, place, and the Nature of the thing ſhould require.</p>
               <p>For though that Mariage, as it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man and woman, contayning an inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable ſociety of life, be of Nature it ſelfe; and (as Deuines and Canoniſts hold) to haue his Originall in the ſtate of innocencie, which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedlie was then ordayned for iſſues ſake, from which a lineall ſucceſſion was alſo inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: yet vntill neceſſity in forced man to make diuiſion of the Bleſſings of God and Nature, the claymes, and rights which follow lineall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to inheritance, were not diſcouered. For all things being common among men many ages were numbred from the worlds beginning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any man laid proper clayme to any thing, as due to himſelf alone. Wherby it well appeares that hereditary ſucceſſion, or Title to a Parents lands or goods, could not then be in vſe, or ſo much as thought of.</p>
               <p>This, I perſwade my ſelfe, was the law of Nature vndepraued. To the which I inclyne my will the ſooner to credit; becauſe, I find that all ſorts of people, as well Chriſtians as others, who haue perfection in Naturall Society, or a perfect Religious life in a Natural and worldly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation of men haue; &amp; do daily imboace this naturall, and bleſſed community. Which happy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16185:9"/>law of Nature (as I haue ſaid) for many age: and without doubt had longer contynued, had not ſinne (which breakes al vnion and depraues all naturall perfection) gotten ſuch dominion in the myndes of men; that in naturall equitie all things could not longer be vſed in common.</p>
               <p>For as ſome being poſſeſſed with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable deſire to get rule and raigne, ſought the oppreſſion of others, by taking from them that fredome which Nature had giué them: ſo others giuen to ſenſuality and idlenes, ſought to liue of other mens labours. Wheras by Natures lawes euery one ought to liue by his proper induſtry, within the rules of iuſtice and honeſty. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon naturall reaſon perſwaded, that all things being deuided, euerie man ſhould knowe his owne: otherwiſe no peace or concord could be maintayned in humane ſociety. For, all things being Common, the way lay open to euery man at his pleaſure to abuſe others, and as it were to rob them of God his Bleſſing.</p>
               <p>Heereupon, Ariſtotle iudged the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all worldlie goods, to haue bene agreable to the law of Nature, which the precept of our Decalogue ſeemes to approue,</p>
               <q>NON FVRTVM FACIES.</q>
               <p>For the Lawe of God is neuer contrarie to the Lawe of Nature: neither doth Nature euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary it ſelfe, though ſome may perhaps think
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16185:9"/>that herein ſhee hath. For albeit at the Creation of all things togeather with man in the ſtate of grace, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munity was intended: yet was it not ſo abſolutely reſolued of by Nature, but that by neceſſity (I meane by fall of man from Gods grace) ſhe did diſpenſe with this law, and left free to mans choyce to imbrace, vpon her war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, either the one or the other, as beſt might fit the time, place, and natures of men, which euer ſynce the world began haue giuen occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the making of all lawes.</p>
               <p>Whereby we ſee, that though Nature giue the grounds to lawes: yet mans vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſtill giues the particuler forme. For Nature creating man, gaue vnto him thoſe worldly bleſſings to vſe well, with warrant either to hold them in Common, or in Proper, as reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from tyme to tyme could beſt perſwade his will. But, when reaſon and will had agreed, that it was fit that euery man ſhould enioy his part in proper; Nature moued man further, and told him, that now he might lawfully think on his ſucceſſion; and not onely liue in his ſpecies, but breath as it were to the worlds end, in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall Poſterity by honorable deeds and vertuous Acts; with which deſire, Nature as a wife mother ſo inflamed man her nobleſt child after his fall from grace, that ſome men by Natures light on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, haue done acts almoſt aboue Nature; and none hath hardlie beene ſo baſe, but deſirous to liue, and leaue an honorable memory behind
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16185:10"/>them.</p>
               <p>Which, that they may the better do, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath not only giuen them power, to leaue their well gotten wealth, but in a manner their habituall vertues to their iſſue; in which this worldly honour (the ſoules worldly lyfe, and vertues temporall reward) may liue free from all-killing tyme. Yet, did ſhe not then by any Commaund, leaue it to any one in particuler, but giuing a generall ſuggeſtion of the fitnes of the thing, left the forme to their beſt diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For had ſhee not done ſoe, all Nations had bene tyed to obſerue one forme, in leauing their goods, and fortunes to their Poſterityes; for Nature being one, without chaunge to all, of neceſſity preſcribes no binding rule to any in particuler, but to all in generall; no man being able to ſay, that this Natures law Commaunds me to do, and yet byndes not any other to do the like. Which is euident in the matter of ſucceſſion, or claymes of inheritance; no one Country obſeruing the forme held by another, or tying it ſelfe without controle to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his owne, as I ſhall hearafter declare.</p>
               <p>For albeit (as I haue ſaid) the coniunction of man and woman, which wee call Marriage, or Matrimony, togeather which the deſire of iſſue, be of Nature, from whence alſo are ſprung not only a diuiſion of goods, and the fortunes of this world: but alſo a laudable deſyre to preſerue a family, and name, by the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16185:10"/>ordination of heyres, to well gotten poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; yet did Nature neuer ſet downe as a law, that thoſe fortunes ſhould be left to the elder brother or younger, or to any one in particuler, or to all, but to whom the Father, being true &amp; free Lord thereof, ſhould beſt deuiſe by will guided by reaſon. For it was neuer yet auerred by any ſound Deuine, Philoſopher, or lawyer, that Nature makes immediatly heyres, but men, whom the poſitiue lawes of euery Country or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne by that forme, and power of law, where ſuch an act ſhould be done. And this is (I preſume) without controle, what the law of Nature commaunded touching the matter in queſtion. Next let vs ſee, what the lawes of God do commaund.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16185:11"/>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That the breach of ſome written lawes of God vpon warrant of the Primarie law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is without ſinne: and that therfore there can be no ſuch right in Primogeniture, which is not in the Fathers power to auoyd, though there were a precept to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as there is not.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Nature, being taken for the principall, and all-producing cauſe of the whole frame of the Vniuerſe with al creatures therein, be nothing els, but the working. Will of the Higheſt, and firſt Moouer, as Deuines and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers do hould; then ſurely muſt Natures law be his will, which he cannot contradict or commaund to the contrary, except he ſhould be contrary to himſelfe, which he cannot. For, what is in God, is God; therfore Conſtant, &amp; Immutable.</p>
               <p>Out of which ground it is eaſily proued: That if the law of God teach that which the law of Nature hath ordained, the right of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance cannot be tyed to any other perſon or perſons, then to thoſe which the Fathers will
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16185:11"/>approues, according to power giuen him by the lawes of the Nations where he liues. Which power deriued from Natures law, cannot erre from the law of God. For whoſoeuer ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider but of Gods Commaundements giuen to man, ſhall well fynd, that God thereby hath ſtill ſeconded his former ordinances giuen by Nature. For ſo long as man kind liued in a ſort, after the innocency which Gods grace in his firſt Creation had wrought in him, God gaue him no other law; but when as by ſinne thoſe ſparks which remayned after his fall were quite extinguiſhed, he gaue him new lawes, yet agreable to Nature.</p>
               <p>As for example, in our preſent affayres. When man had made by Natures priuiledge partition of Gods and Natures bleſſings; then God ſaid to his people by the mouth of Moyſes, Thou ſhalt nor ſteale: Thou ſhalt not couet thy Neighbours houſe, his wife, his oxe, his Aſſe, or any thing that is his. As alſo, Thou ſhalt not kill. Which with all other his Comaundements teaching what ſinne is, are agreable to the law of Nature, yet are diſpenſed withall as far as the lawes of Nature euer permitted. For, though that the expreſſe Comaundement of God be; Thou ſhalt not couet any thing that is thy Neighbours, nor kill, yet in ſome caſes, both may lawfwlly be done. The one in extreme want of preſent food: the other in defence of life and goods; in which, the law of God is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16185:12"/>good, by the originall law of Nature, which made all for the ſuſtenance of man; and gaue leaue to defend life with the loſſe of anothers bloud, yea life, if otherwiſe it cannot be. Vpon which ground I argue thus.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the law of God did at this preſent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maund (which indeed it doth not) that the in heritance ſhould be left to any one particuler perſon, and namely to the elder Brother: yet in ſome Caſes it would not bynd the Father to obſerue it. For as in the former Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements vpon ſome conſiderations, the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement may be diſpenſed withall, ſo in this. For, it is not ſufficient to be the elder Brother, or the neareſt in bloud to gaine an inheritance, in the Caſe which I haue now propoſed; for other circumſtances muſt concurre, which if they be wanting, bare propinquity or ancienty of bloud may iuſtly be reiected: and he that is ſecond, third, fourth, fifth, or laſt may lwafully be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the firſt, and this by al law diuyne and humane, and by all Reaſon, Conſcience, and Cuſtome of nations Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>For if it ſhould fall out that the next in bloud, ſhould be a Naturall foole, or a madman; or being taken by the Turkes or Mores in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, and brought vp in their religion would maintaine the ſame: or if any other ſuch acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, miniſtring cauſe of iuſt exception ſhould fall out; is it likely that any law would allow, that ſuch a man ſhould be admitted to the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16185:12"/>Wherefore how idly ſhould they talk, that would haue that it was his birthright, or that God and Nature had made him heire, ſince that neither God nor Nature doth imedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately make heires, as I haue ſayd before. True it is, that God and Nature makes men, who by the mediation of the lawes and cuſtomes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may come to be heires. Vpon which ground our cómon Lawyers ſay, that no heyres are borne, but men and law make them.</p>
               <p>True it is, that in holy Writ, great reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect is had of the firſt begotten, &amp; a bleſſing is held to come to parents thereby. But this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (I preſuppoſe) to be, that therby the feare of ſterility was taken away, which in the old Law was held to be a great puniſhment of God, and in reſpect thereof parents had of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and by the nationall lawes and cuſtoms, a great regard of their firſt begotten, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred them to the better part of their poſſeſſions: yet not by any commaund from God, as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to bind his elect people vnder paine of ſinne. For, had any ſuch Law bound them, vnder ſuch a penalty; then ſhould it bynd all Chriſtians now, on the ſame conditions. For we ſee it by generall practiſe of all countryes to be otherwiſe. Therefore it followes directly, that it was not Gods Comaundement, but a Nationall Law. For God both is, and ever was one, without chaunge to all his people; and ſo euer were, and wilbe his Lawes poſitiue,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16185:13"/>made for them that truely worſhip him.</p>
               <p>The clayme which <hi>Eſau</hi> made to his Birthright was not by the law of God, as ſome ignorantly affirme, but by the lawes of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. For, ſhould the law of God haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded it, it had bene ſinne in his Mother, and brother, by cunning to haue gotten it from him. Neither could the Father or the State wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they liued, vpon no iuſt cauſe knowne but to God alone, without ſinne, haue ſetled the ſame vpon his Brother. <hi>Iacob,</hi> as it was, and as it may ſeeme by allowance from God, and as it may be iudged by the ſuceſſe. Whereby it is thought, that God ordained it as a puniſhment of the one, and bleſſing of the other: which by the permiſſion of ſinne to be committed, God doth neuer do.</p>
               <p>Neither did the Nationall law or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Iewes (as it is ſaid) abſolutly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the Father to leaue vnto his firſt begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, all, or the greateſt part of his goods and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. But if in caſe he died, not diſpoſing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by act in his life, or will at his death, then the cuſtome of the Nation, layd a double portion on the eldeſt or firſt begotten, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the reſt proportionably.</p>
               <p>By all which you may gather; that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the law of God, or man, in this caſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould haue the inheritance; but power to do the contrary was giuen to the Father in his life tyme; euen by the law it ſelfe.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16185:13"/>For many Deuines hold, that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſelling his Birthright (as it is termed) ſould not goods, or lands, but his clayme of being high Preiſt after his Father, which by cuſtome was to come to him, being his Fathers eldeſt ſonne. Of which dignity God ſeing him vnfit, permitted him to paſſeaway his right in his Fathers life, as we read in holy writ, and which God ſeemed to approue. And thus (I hope) this objection is anſwered.</p>
               <p>Further, if it were true, that the effect of Elderſhip were ſuch by the law of God, as ſome paſſionately defend: that is, that the whole inheritance ſhould of right pertaine to the eldeſt; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſure it followeth by good conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; that there ſhould, nor euer could, haue bene but one temporall Lord of all the world. For of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity <hi>Adams</hi> inheritance ſhould haue gone ſtill to the next in bloud; which how abſurd it is, let all men iudge.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, we read, that <hi>Nöe</hi> hauing three ſonnes, and the whole world to leaue vnto them, gaue it not all to the Eldeſt, but equally deuided it among them, and their poſterity, as all authenticall hiſtories do witnes. God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring obedience of children to parents, promiſed a reward, ſaying, Honour thy Father &amp; Mother, that thy dayes may be long in the land which the Lord ſhall giue thee. This ſurely was not ſpoken to one, but to all the children of men. For with God there is no exception of perſons: but as a iuſt and pions Father, he giues euery one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16185:14"/>according to his deſerts: <hi>Terram autem dedit filijs hominum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We read alſo in holy writ, how the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall child, being weary or his Fathers houſe, came vnto him, and boldly ſayd: <hi>Pater, da mihi portionem ſubſtantiae meae, quae me contingit.</hi> This child of which the Goſpell ſpeaks, was the you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brother: yet you ſee how boldly he ſayd: giue vnto me that portion of goods which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to me. By which words it is euident, that a diuiſion, or partition of a Fathers fortunes was then in vſe: and that any child as well you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as elder had power by law, to demaund his legitimate, or childes part, according to the Nature of the Ciuill and Canon Law, as you haue heard. For the words following in the text are theſe: <hi>Et diuiſit ſubſtantiam illis.</hi> Thus we ſee, that the priuiledge of Elderſhip was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; which now in our countrey by cuſtome onely is gotten to be of ſuch force.</p>
               <p>But it may be obiected, that this was a parable onely (as indeed it was) and cannot be alledged as law. True it is; yet it cannot be denied, but that all ſimilies, parables, or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which euer were alledged by the wiſe and learned, to repreſent the truth, haue euer bene deriued from the cuſtomes and nature of things, according to the knowne truth in that tyme, place, and to thoſe to whome the ſpeach, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is directed. And ſhall we think, that our Sauiour Chriſt being wiſdom and truth it ſelfe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16185:14"/>treating of ſo important an affaire as he did then in the Ghoſpell, would vſe an vnknowne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or ſtriue to make the truth appeare to our weake vnderſtandings by a Parable which in equity could not be true? Noe ſurely. For it appeares by <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſucceding to his Father <hi>Dauid,</hi> that <hi>Dauid</hi> had power by the lawes of god and man, to giue his Kingdome to the worthieſt, which hedeeming to be <hi>Salomon,</hi> gaue vnto him his Kingdome, though he was the yongeſt ſonne.</p>
               <p>Neither was there any iuſt exception made againſt <hi>Adonias</hi> his eldeſt Brother, or againſt ſome other of his Brethren, why they ſhould be diſinherited by their Father <hi>Dauid,</hi> contrary to the common practiſe of thoſe tymes, in ſetling inheritances. But, the only knowne reaſon of this act in Scripture, was <hi>Dauid</hi> promiſe made to <hi>Salomons</hi> Mother, togeather with her great intreaty made to <hi>Dauid</hi> to performe the ſame. Which ſurely he would not haue done, except hee had found a lawfull power in himſelfe, to haue executed the ſame. And thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what may be ſaid out of Scripture, or law of God in our preſent queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16185:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> That nations begining to deniſe ſundry formes of ſetling Inherit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nces, the Romanes eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially therin reſpected the free power of Fathers; the right of Children to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eſtates begining only at their Fathers Death.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING now declared in the former chapter what the lawes of God, and Nature doe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne of our preſent queſtion; we inted to examine in breif, what is comaunded by the law of Man, aſwell ciuill of other Nations as common of our owne Gontry. And firſt touching the ciuill Law thus.</p>
               <p>Though that all Law, which euer had but the name or credit of Law, doth ſurely deriue her originall from the Law of Nature; whereupon <hi>Cicero</hi> many hundreth yeares ſynce ſaid, that the ground of all law making, is to be taken from the chief law, which was borne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any law was written, or Citty builded: yet do they differ much in forme. For as it is no law, but tyranny, which wholy diſagrees with the law of Nature, as Ariſtotle ſaith:ſo if it agree
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16185:15"/>in al with the law of Nature without limitation, or difference it muſt of force be the very law of Nature it ſelf, and not the law of man. Which ſurely is nothing els, then a temper, or forme of equity, drawne by right reaſon from the grounds of Natures lawes; according as tyme, place, and the Natures of men either gaue or ſhall giue the occaſion. For though new lawes be dayly made of new &amp; ſeuerall accidents: yet all are agreable to the old, and ancient grounds of reaſon in Nature, the iuſt Mother of all law. Wherefore, hauing ſet downe before, what the law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is, touching the matter in queſtion, I ſhall need only now to ſhew, what temper or forme hath thereunto bene added by the Ciuill Lawyer.</p>
               <p>After that mankind was inforced (yet by Natures warrant) as I haue ſaid to make a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Bleſſings of God, and Nature: and that men were poſſeſſed by the ſame right of goods and lands, which they deſyred to leaue to poſterity; law-makers, and in particuler the Ciuilian, deuiſed by little and little certayne formes of inheritance, and ordination of heyres, at the firſt ſomwhat rigorous; giuing to Parents power of life and death ouer their Children, &amp; a free diſpoſition of all their fortunes to any one of them in his life: but dying inteſtate, then all which was the Fathers, to be equally deuided among the Children, as wel daughters as ſonns. Which Conſtitution was afterward vpon good
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16185:16"/>grounds altered: The Father being bound to leaue euery Child a portion, which the Ciuill Lawyer calleth a <hi>legitimate,</hi> others a Patrimony; which at the firſt was the eight part of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſubſtance equally to be deuided (as I haue ſaid:) which after a while ſeeming little, the law commaunded, that the fourth part ſhould be left without controule: except, that vpon iuſt cauſe the Teſtator did diſinherite him or them who by courſe of law were to ſucceed him: ſtill vpholding the former lawes, that aſwel daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as ſonnes, ſhould equally ſucceed to their Parents dying inteſtate; herein aſſigning fourteene Cauſes, why an heyre might lawfully be diſinherited.</p>
               <p>Many hundred yeares paſſed, from the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of the Ciuill law, and before that it was ordayned by force of law that Parents ſhould leaue a Childes part (as it is now called) or that he could not diſinherit, without expreſſing the cauſe thereof in his laſt Will: yet, in all this tyme, nor vntill this preſent day, the priuiledg of engroſſing all by <hi>Primogeniture</hi> was not once heard of, or at leaſt wiſe not admitted, but rather excluded; as by many texts in the ſame Law it well appeares: The end of the Imperiall, or Roman Ciuill law, being only to maintaine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Iuſtice inthree ſhort precepts, <hi>Liue honeſtly; Hurt no Man; Gine vnto euery one his owne.</hi> So he who obſerues theſe three, fulfills this law, yea the law of Nature, from whence this law is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16185:16"/>ſprung. Now, if any Brother can proue, that his Father either in life by deed, or by will at his death diſpoſing of his goods &amp; lands, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then I haue ſet downe, doth none act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe three; then why ſhould he not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelf, either with the fruits of his Fathers loue, or his owne deſerts whatſoeuer they be.</p>
               <p>True it is, that in Naturall iuſtice, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren during their Fathers life, haue <hi>Ius ad rem,</hi> and not <hi>Ius in re</hi> to a Fathers goods. Whereupon the Law calleth them <hi>Quaſibonorum patris Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</hi> Which their right onely takes effect after their Fathers death. For during life, hee hath power to alter, alien, ſel, and giue as it ſhal pleaſe him according to forme of law; but being dead without will, or diſpoſition therof, they fall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his children (as I haue ſaid) according to the law of nations. This law imbraceth a two fold iuſtice; the one in exchange, the other in diſtribution. The firſt hath not to do with our cauſe: the other ſurely rather commends, then condemns a Father, who vpon good occaſion, that is, for the bad demerits of his eldeſt ſonne, and for the preſeruation only of his family, ſhall giue, or conuey his lands &amp; goods to the yonger. For the Nature of diſtributiue iuſtice, is not only to giue proportionably to the well deferuing: but alſo to forbeare to place benefits vpon any one who ſhall abuſe them; or vſe them to any other end, then to that good for which they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16185:17"/>were lent him, and hee ſhall leaue them. And this is, <hi>Ius ſuum vnicuique tribuere.</hi> For no man can giue or ſell his goods to an euill end, or to any one whom he aſſures himſelfe will vſe them to the diſhonour of God; or the wrong of thoſe who ſhall liue with him, or by him; of which I will ſpeak more in the laſt chapter, being there to handle what a Father may in conſcience do, or not do, in our preſent queſtion, with ſinne, and without ſinne. And thus much of the Ciuill and Canon Lawyers auerment of an elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers right to his Fathers fortunes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16185:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That the preſent cuſtome in our Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntrey of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all, or almoſt all to the Eldeſt, was neuer ſo begun, that it meant to exclude iuſt remedies for ſuch euills, as should growe out of the abuſe of that cuſtome, when it may make Fathers guilty of their ſonnes faults, and of their families ruines.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue of purpoſe reſerued to treate of the lawes of our countrey in the laſt place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (I aſſure my ſelfe) that they are of moſt force to ſway the matter in queſtion. For many things may be permitted by the lawes of God and Nature; and yet they on the contrary are forbiden, or practiſed by courſe of law in ſeuerall States of the world, as the law-makers, and the cuſtomes of the countries do allow or comaund. I do confeſſe, that the generall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of our tyme among parents is to leaue either all, or the moſt part of their lands to their eldeſt begotten ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. This without all queſtion, was (as it hath bene ſaid) firſt deuiſed in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages, for the preſeruation of a family, and to raiſe ſome one, who might be a comfort to his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16185:18"/>brothers, ſiſters, and family, and in whom his progenitors vertues might line to the world. Moreouer, I will not deny, but the partition of lands may bring, in the end, a goodly eſtate to nothing, or to ſo little, as it may be like an A to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in the ſunne: yet I find in Naturall reaſon, that, <hi>ex nihilo nihil fit,</hi> or at leſt, that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haud facilè emergunt, quorum virtutibus obstat Res ang iſta domi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if men do faile of thoſe happy ends to which this generall cuſtome ſhould guide, then would I wiſh, that they would not vſe that for their deſtruction, which was meant for their preſeruation. For who doth not ſee, in theſe our tymes, may vnbridled youths, to be ſo violently carried away with the humor of ſpending, that they neglect brother, and ſiſter; yea, bring to extreame miſery their Naturall Mothers after their Fathers death by their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriſtines. What help for this hath law left vnto vs? no means to put a bridle to theſe vnruly colts if they become heires according to the cuſtome of our tyme? no truely. For ſome ſtarting hole wilbe found to vnty the knot which a Fathers care once tyed. How then? muſt many an hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and well-de ſeruing brother and ſiſter, be left to the mercy of this whirlwind? There is no neceſſity in it. For our law hath giuen power to a Father, &amp; free will to diſpoſe of his owne, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as reaſon ſhall guide his will, without all obligation to his heire. Beſides, this cuſtome
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16185:18"/>takes place, onely after a Fathers death, if he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe not of what is his by deed in life, or by will at his death.</p>
               <p>But leaſt my words be more generally taken, then they are meant; I meane thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are poſſeſſed of their lands in fee, or fee-tayle; that is, are abſolute of themſelues, and haue not vpon good conſideration, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaied their lands from themſelues. For all our lawyers do agree, that ſuch parents may alien, ſell, and giue by power of our law their lands to whome they wil, without reſpect of perſon or elderſhip. But me thinks I heare one ſay, that the cuſtome is otherwiſe; and that this cuſtome is a law. True, it is the cuſtome. But let vs ſee whether it bindes <hi>ſub peccato,</hi> or as a cuſtome, which rather inuites then commaunds. There neuer was any comaund to tye a Father vnder a penalty which admits no limitation; but it was euer left indifferent, and then only to take place where former prouiſion according to courſe of law is not made; thé ſurely a parent is free from this deuouring cuſtome, and may in good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration preuent what euill it may bring to his poſterity, yea reaſon comaunds it ſhould be ſo. For, <hi>Interest reipublicae vt quilibet re ſua bene vtatur,</hi> as ſaith the ciuill law. For if a man can ney ther ſell, nor ſet, much leſſe can hee giue any thing to another, which he thinks in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will vſe it to the diſhonour of God, the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of himſelfe, or others.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16185:19"/>
               <p>Some Deuines hould, that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſell, or let an houſe to any that he thinks aſſuredly would make thereof a ſtewes; or to ſel, giue, or lend a weapon to a man who intends therewith to do murder. Excomunications are impoſed on them, who ſell armes offenſiue, or defenſiue to <hi>Turks,</hi> though they be not aſſured that they will vſe them againſt Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Thus wee ſee, the rule of conſcience, not onely to commaund a man to vſe well thoſe fortunes which God hath beſtowed vpon him: but forbids him, either vpon affection, or gaine, to part with them to others who wil abuſe them; leaſt he be partaker of others ſinne; which a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent may be after death who leaueth his lands to a deſperate vnthrift. But what religion, and conſcience doth commaund, ſhalbe declared in the following chapter. In which vpon grounds drawne out of theſe former foure Chapters, it ſhalbe argued, what ſin may be contracted by the parting of an eſtate among ſonns, or by diſinhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting of an eldeſt ſonne, vpon iuſt cauſe; and vnto whom the Father is only tyed by the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Countrey, without obligation of promiſe, or contract in Marriage, which may alter the Caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:16185:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That it is no offence before God for a Father, being tenant in fee-ſimple, to diſinherit the eldeſt, or to parcell his eſtate vpon cauſe: &amp; that extreme vices of Heyres apparent, togeather with the fewer meanes which younger Brothers haue now to liue on, then heeretoſore, cryeth out againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE right of theſe inſociable inheritours, of which wee now treat, may grow (as I magine) out of three titles, or claymes, which they may pretend to a Fathers inheritance, &amp; wherby it may be deemed (as they think) ſinne in a Father, vpon what deſert ſoeuer, to barre them of the faid right. Theſe three tytles, are Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, Cuſtome, and Entaile. Of ech ſeuerally. And of the firſt, which is Purchaſe; ſurely in the iudgment of the good and learned, there is no queſtion in law, or conſcience, but that a Sonne ioyned Purchaſer with his Father, hath <hi>Ius in re,</hi> and by equity muſt, ſuruyuing his Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite ſuch lands as were purchaſed in their names. Now of the other two, though it be as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16185:20"/>cleere, as the noone light; that a Lord in Fee ſimple, or Tenant in taile, may ſell, or giue by courſe of our Common law, at his pleaſure, all ſuch lauds held by him in that kind, according to thoſe formes of law, which the learned in our lawes haue, and can ſet downe: yet there ſeemes to ariſe a great difficulty how ſuch an act, or acts may in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience be executed. I haue heard ſome ſay, in this our Caſe, <hi>Summum ius, ſumma iniuria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe points therefore I will ſpeake, <hi>ſaluo meliori iudicio,</hi> what may in Conſcience, vpon good and iuſt occaſion giuen by the ſonne to his Father, be put in execution. It is well knowne to all diuines (as I haue ſaid) that holy writ hath not preſcribed any direct, or preciſe forme to the Children of God, whereby they are bound in Conſcience to diſpoſe of their lands &amp; goods, but hath abſolutely left them to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of their Country, where any act of that kind ſhalbe executed, only as confirming all formes of deuiſes which by publick conſent, and authority, either haue, or ſhall in rightfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be deuiſed, or ordained.</p>
               <p>Out of this ground and others before mentioned; let vs examyne, whether a Father parting his fortunes by power of law, and on iuſt cauſe; ſhall do a wrongfull, and a ſinfull act as ſome pretend to make it.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe, that euery act in it ſelf, or by Circumſtance euill, and which vpon no occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16185:20"/>can be iuſtified, is both before God, and man ſinne; and is by no means to be executed by a Chriſtian. But that the parting of an inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or the diſinheriting of an eldeſt ſonne, vpon iuſt cauſe, and according to courſe of Law, is an act of that nature, doth not appeare. For I do not fynd, that either the Law of Nature, or grace, nor yet the Lawes of man, common, ciuil, or Canon, euer forbad ſuch acts, whereby ſinne may be imputed to thoſe who do them on good conſiderations. Sure I am, that the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and Ciuill Law, are ſo far from forbidding them, that they commaund, as a thing in equity, the Father either to deuide his inheritance, or allow him, according to his affection, to giue to one, more then to another: yet with this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſo; that he who hath the leaſt haue his childes part, which the Law doth alſo aſſigne, except on iuſt deſert he do diſinherit any one; which at this day may, yea muſt be by will, with the cauſe of diſinheriſion named therein. Of which cauſes the Imperiall Lawes haue ſet downe fourteene, as it ſhall well appeare to them who are deſyrous to vnderſtand more thereof. So it is euident, that by theſe two Lawes, no ſinne can grow vpon ſuch acts, being done vpon their warrant, and vpon ſuch conſideration, as hath bene before often by me ſet downe.</p>
               <p>As for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Lawes of our Realme ſure it is, that they allow no leſſe, and with a greater preuiledge. For a man may by this law, giue his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16185:21"/>landes held in Fee, either by deed in his life, or by will at his death, to any of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; yea, to a ſtranger, without rendring a reaſon why he doth ſo. True it is, that a Father, not diſpoſing thereof in ſuch ſort, the Cuſtome giues the whole eſtate to the eldeſt: yet in ſome parts of our Country, the youngeſt Brother by Cuſtome is to haue the land, held by ſome kind of tenure, if the Father in his life tyme do not diſpoſe thereof.</p>
               <p>As yet therefore I cannot ſee how any ſinne is commited, or contracted by the former acts, being neither done againſt the law of God, or man, as we haue proued; except it ſhould be ſaid to be ſinne, not to leaue it to the power of a cuſtome; which cannot be except the former law ſhalbe proued not to be of force, and no way to be executed, which can no way bee done. For though I muſt confeſſe, that the cuſtome of leauing the child-eſtate to the eldeſt ſonne, hath of later times bene much imbraced by our Gentry, for the preſeruation of their families, for which it was inuented: For the tymes haue ſo ruled, that men of ſort being either idle, or not poſſeſſed with a couetous humor, haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended themſelues with their Fathers fortunes, and haue preferred their younger ſonns by thoſe means, which the tymes did affoard; which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better then now they are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely by many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable courſes; as either by ſeruice of ſpirituall men, whereby many were
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16185:21"/>raiſed or by profeſſing a ſpirituall life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the younger brother hath oftentimes in ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ſtept before the elder. But this manner of life is not ſo gratefull to our Engliſh gentlemens Natures as it hath bene.</p>
               <p>The trade of the Merchant, the Military profeſſion, the Courtyers life, aduanced many more, then now they do; and laſtly, the elder brothers were the of better temper in ſpending: and if they had no humour to get, yet had they a care to keep what was left vnto them; and euer held themſelues bound by religion to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for their younger brothers and ſiſters, left to their diſpoſe, which now is far otherwiſe. For an elder brother is found to ſpend more in a yeare idlie, then would prefer, or maintaine a whoſe familie noblie; and to ſuffer their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and ſiſters to ſhift, which as theſe times ſhape, is oftentymes to liue either lewdly, or moſt miſerably: being forced either to forget their good education, or to lay aſide all badges of gentrie, who otherwiſe with ſome reaſonable helps, might do God, their Countrey, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily much honour.</p>
               <p>Since wee haue gone ſo far, let vs ſee on what grounds this cuſtome firſt hath riſen. Surely for the maintenance of a family, yet led with, an ambition, at the example of princes, who finding ſome difficulties in the admitting of many to a gouernement, and feling what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences the parting of an eſtate brought,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16185:22"/>deuiſed that one ſhould gouerne; ſometimes the worthieſt, ſometimes the eldeſt was elected, according as the order was agreed vpon, and yet the other brothers were mainteyned like Princes. And thus, cuſtome alſo among them hath bene broken, without imputation of ſinne. For to go no further then our later times; it is well knowne that <hi>Ferdinand (Charles</hi> the fifth his brother) being ſetled in the Empyre, deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his eſtate. To <hi>Maximilian</hi> his eldeſt ſonn, he left the Empyre, with <hi>Austria, Hungaria,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia.</hi> To <hi>Charles</hi> his ſecond ſonne, <hi>Styria, Carinthia,</hi> and other dominions, And to <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> the youngeſt, he gaue the Earldome of <hi>Tyrol.</hi> All which, if in his life tyme he had not diſpoſed of, had come to the eldeſt. <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, late king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> gaue to his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the 17. Prouinces, which were of right to haue deſcended to his ſonne after his death, if he had not diſpoſed thereof in his life tyme. This is, and was deemed lawfull by the Diuines of this age, otherwiſe ſurely they would neuer haue done it.</p>
               <p>But doth this cuſtome in meaner degrees work that effect which it hath done in them? No truely. For as wee haue proued, it is rather the ouerthrow then the preſeruation of many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. And let vs ſee withall, whether families florithed not as much and more then now they do, before this cuſtome was receiued. <hi>Liuic</hi> ſaith that three hundred of the <hi>Faby,</hi> being all of one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16185:22"/>name and family, iſſued out of Rome gates at one tyme on their owne coſt, to the defence of their citty, which was done before this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome was dreamed of.</p>
               <p>In Scotland 300. of the name and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the <hi>Fraſers,</hi> gentlemen, were at one tyme ſlaine in a fight by their enemies neighbors; and 140. gentlemen of one name in Yorkſhire wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon their chiefe, or principall man of their houſe being at that time high Sheriffe. In other countreys many Noble families, from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans downward, haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued where this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e hath beene deemed vniuſt, as by their lawes it is manifeſt: whereas in our contrey, in theſe our tymes, if there be one familie in a Shire, which is of three hundred yeares continuance, verie many others are ſcarce of fiue deſcents in a bloud.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould our age then, ſeing the fruit of this cuſtome to be ſo ſmall, imbrace it with ſuch zeale, as to deeme the breach thereof, being warranted for good and iuſt by the Law of God, of Nature, and of man to be a ſinne? Is it poſſible that it is held both lawfull, and expedient, for the preſeruation of a family, that degrees of kindred ſhould be diſpenſed with to mary, being knowne contrary to the general practiſe of gods Church: and can it be lawfull before God and man, for preſeruation of our goods, to venture our liues, and to kill a Theife who ſhall aſſault vs, and that perhaps for a trifle: and yet that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16185:23"/>for preſeruation of our whole eſtate, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance of a family, it ſhalbe held ſinne to break a bare cuſtome, vnder no penalty obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, yea alwaies allowed by law? I haue neuer heard, that a cuſtome was of force, to abiogate a law ſo far that it ſhould be deemed a ſinne to follow the ſaid law; though it haue power to diſpenſe with the law, which other wiſe to break were ſinne, eſpecially, when as the law is both more pious, and more naturall then the cuſtom is. For how far is it from the law of Nature, and from the practiſe of Fatherlie piety, the Father dying inteſtate, the eldeſt ſonne to become abſolute Lord of all his Fathers lands, and not to be bound by law to prouide for brother or ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but at his owne good liking. <hi>Aliud tempus alios mores postutat.</hi> Men of vertue, men of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; vertue, both now, and in former ages in this our countrey haue broken this cuſtome, as the world knowes, vpon good conſideration, and iuſt cauſes; not vpon ſpleene, or falſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions perſwaded to leaue their fortunes to ſtrangers, or to a luſtſuil iſſue, as ſome haue done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:16185:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That Fathers being tenants in Fee-tayle, may likewiſe without ſcruple of Conſcience, diſcontinue the state-taile vpon cauſe, and deuiſe the ſame at their reaſonable plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING treated largely, and (as I preſume) proued ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, that lands held in fee-ſimple, may either be parted, or vpon iuſt cauſe wholy giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away to a younger ſonne; I intend now to ſpeak of the lawfull freedome of a Father in like ſort, and on the ſame cauſes; moued to diſpoſe of his lands intailed: of which there ſeemes more doubt then of the former.</p>
               <p>Euery humane act, which of it ſelf is not forbidden by the law of God or Nature, is to be iudged good or euill, lawfull or vnlawfull; either by the lawe of the place where the act is done or by intention of him who ſhall do the act. For, as the law of God commaunds ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things to be done, &amp; other things to be auoided, vnder paine of ſinne: ſo the third ſort of actions are left free (by the ſaid authority) from ſinne;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16185:24"/>except the law of man ſhall forbid them, and ſo make them ſinne; or els euill intention make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (being of themſelues lawfull) to be a ſinne, and vnlawful; according to that principle of Moral Philoſophy, <hi>Finis ſpecifical actum.</hi> For as an act of it ſelf lawful, being done againſt law is ſinne: ſo a good act comaunded by law, yet done with an euill intention, may be ſinne.</p>
               <p>Out of theſe grounds let vs ſee, whether the Common law of our Countrey, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of a Father, which are to be the Iudges of our Cauſe, can allow the cutting offan entaile, the parting of an inheritance, or (vpon propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable cauſe) the diſinheriting of a ſonne. Firſt, it is cleere, that the act of it ſelf, by law, may be done; but whether ſuch an act be <hi>ſummu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ius,</hi> which may be <hi>ſumma iniuria,</hi> that is the doubt. What ſhalbe the triall? By other lawes, it is either made lawfull, or left indifferent. Our law which makes this tye, giues leaue to vndo it without any exception. Ergo, to a good end, and vpon iuſt cauſe it may be done. But it may be ſaid, that the eldeſt ſonne during this entaile, is <hi>quaſi Dominus,</hi> yet hauing neither <hi>Dominium directum,</hi> nor <hi>indirectum,</hi> he, during his Fathers life, hath only <hi>ius ad rem,</hi> and not <hi>in re.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by no chaunge is forbidden to be made by the Father, according to the forme of the law vnder which he liueth, and by which the ſonne is to make clayme, if the Father ſhall create no new eſtate in his life. For it is lawfull for euery man
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16185:24"/>to diſpoſe of his owne, as far as the law ſhall permit him; if it be not forbidden by ſome other law; but ſuch an act is not forbidden by any other law; <hi>Ergo</hi> it is lawfull and no ſinne.</p>
               <p>But it may be ſaid, that the intention of him who entailed the land was, that it ſhould not be vntyed, or the ſtate changed. To which I anſwere. That no act done by law, can be free from chaung, further, or longer, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law that made it a bynding act ſhall allow. And it is well knowne to the learned in our lawes, that euery mans intention is to be conſtrued according to law, by which his act, and intentions are directed. Whereupon the <hi>Ciuilian</hi> ſaith in like Caſes, <hi>valeat quantum valire potest.</hi> Neither is it thought, that any man, who conuayeth his lands by entaile, can intend an act beyond law; or deſyre that his ſonne, whom he makes te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nant entaile (as our lawyers tearme him) ſhall in no caſe no, not for the preſeruation of his family, or relief of many others of his Children, haue power to cut off this entaile, and to be able to alien, ſell, or giue his lands, as reaſon, law, and religion ſhall permit. For it may be iudged, that he who doth an act to a good end, as namely to preſerue his family, wil alwaies aſſent to another act, which ſhall with better aſſurance then his owne, ſtrengthen his intention. To the former conſiderations we may add, what incoueniences may follow of this generall poſition. For if in Conſcience the whole inheritance of the Father,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16185:25"/>is to come without comtroule to the eldeſt ſonne, then muſt it of neceſſity be inferied, that the Father, without this conſent, cannot giue to pious vſes, or ſet out for the aduancement of his other Children any other thing after his death. So that if God ſhould bleſſe a Father with many Children, and croſſe him with as many misfortunes; his other Children, and all other his pious intentions ſhould be prouided for only at his ſonnes, or heyres courteſy. Which how abſurd it is all men know. For hereupon all dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to pious vſes, and to younger Brothers for their preferment, may be called in queſtion.</p>
               <p>It is an ordinary thing in theſe our tymes, when the land is let to the Heyre generall, to alter the eſtate, if the land ſo conueyed ſhall come to Daughters, and to leaue it to a Brothers ſonne, or to ſome other of the ſame name, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture many degrees remoued, for preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the name and family. If this may be deemed lawful and no ſinne, being done againſt a well deſeruing child, for whom Nature, and her deſerts plead her worthy to be her Fathers heyre: then without all compare, if the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of a name and family, might not iuſtly be laboured for, according to power giuen by the law of God and man: what may be lawfully acted againſt an vnthrifty heyre, who in any reaſonable mans iudgment is likly in his ſhrowd, to bury the memory of all his Anceſtors vertues, which ſhould liue in him, and his ofſpring, as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16185:25"/>his forefathers haue done in theirs.</p>
               <p>It is neyther new, nor ſtraung, in the practiſe of our tymes, in cauſes of this Nature, to ouerthrow in tended perpetuities, and by act of parliament to giue leaue vpon ſom good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations to ſell lands, which otherwiſe by no lawes can be ſold from the heyre, the Father being but tennant only for tearme of his life. Which ſurely by no power vnder God could be done, if the thing in it ſelf be vnlawful &amp; ſinne. Out of which it may be argued <hi>a fortiori:</hi> If power may be giuen to a Father being tennant for tearme of life, to ſell his ſonnes lands, onely to pay his owne debts (peraduenture idly made) though it be to the ouerthrowe of his Familie; becauſe naturall equity (ſay they) doth wil, that euery one ſhould be relieued with his owne, for ſo it may be deemed, though in loue to his child hee hath paſſed the eſtate, yet that he ought to be preſerued from thraldome therewith in his neceſſity: which if it be ſo (as all men do confeſſe it) how reaſonable a thing, yea how comendable, and farre from ſinne is it, for a Father truely Lord of his owne, without all tye of law, either deuine, or humane (as I haue proued) to diſpoſe of his lands, to the honour of God, and comfort of his family, to a yonger ſonne, when as it is moſt probable that the elder will neither vſe it to the one, nor the other, but rather to nouriſh ſinne and ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16185:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That vnthriftines is one knowne name of many hidden ſinns, and is alone a ſufficient cauſe of diſinheriſon, proued by the Law of God and Man.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING thus vpon good conſideration beyond my firſt intention (as it appeareth by my Preface) enlardged this my diſcourſe with the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Chapter; I haue reſolued my ſelfe, vpon my Readers fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and on the former grounds, to argue one queſtion more, which I hold verie neceſſary for the perfecting of this ſmall work: which is; <hi>whether a Father may diſinherite his eldeſt ſonne, or heire at common law, for ſuch an vnthriftines as in moſt mens iudgements, is like to be the ruine of his family?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though many foule ſinnes, beſydes the abuſing of gods bleſſings, be concomitant to vnthriftynes, yet becauſe they are not apparant to the world, and <hi>de abſcondit is non iudicat Praetor,</hi> I will only breifly argue, whether in reaſon, or conſcience a deſperate vnthrift may be diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited.</p>
               <p>It is well knowne to all the wiſe, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16185:26"/>temperate, whoſe iudgments paſſion doth not ouerſway, how great an enemy prodigality, or vnthriftynes is to all manner of goodnes; and how cunningly ſhe not onely hinders the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all vertues in thoſe in whome ſhe reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: but alſo vniuſtly oftentymes cuts off the vertuous reward of many a worthy predeceſſor, yea, giues occaſion to the euill to detract, to the good to ſuſpect their deſerts. All which, how great a wrong it is to a Noble family, I leaue to the indifferent reader to cenſure. I will not deny but there may be many ſinns in a man, which in the ſight of God, and iudgment of men, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are more heynous, and deſerue afar greater damnation then Prodigality doth: yet, ſince that ſins in this world are to be puniſhed,<note place="margin">Thoſe ſinnes more pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable which are more off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſiue to common ſociety, though leſſe hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler Nature.</note> not as they are in themſelues, but as they by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance are offenſiue to the ſociety, peace, and honour of mankind, which God and Nature, euer as the reward to all morall vertues, and as the chief end of mans life, intended. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vſury, detraction, forgery, adultery, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſwearing, and drunkenneſſe, all which and many more, which are as greiuous offences in the eye of heauen, as theft, ſhould be puniſhed with death, as theft is. But ſince they do not offend ſo much the peace of a publique weale (at which the Ciuill magiſtrate aymes) as theft doth; they are not cenſured with ſuch ſeuere puniſhment at it is. All which ſhewes directly, that offences by circumſtance are made in a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16185:27"/>Ciuill ſociety againſt which they are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, either great error leſſer; and are accordingly to be puniſhed: and no leſſe doth the reaſon, and righ rule of ſtate commaund.</p>
               <p>Out of which grounds it is euident, that all formes of gouernement do moſt puniſh that offender, who directly or indirectly ſeeks to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe the peace, or ouerthrow the liberty, or diſgrace the ſtate wherin he liues: yet many greater offences then theſe may be committed, as Inceſt, and Apoſtaſy, which are not ſo ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely puniſhed by the Ciuill Magiſtrate. For euery one, to whome God hath giuen power on earth, doth chiefly ſeek the end, for which his power from aboue is giuen vnto him; and doth cenſure and puniſh in the higheſt degree thoſe offences, which tend to the ouerthrowe of a well ſetled ſtate, and by good and lawfull power confirmed.</p>
               <p>Now to come vpon theſe premiſſes to the matter in queſtion, &amp; to apply that which hath beene ſayd to our purpoſe. It is well knowne to the world, that a family is a ciuill ſociety, yea the only common weale which God and Nature firſt ordayned, and from which all ſocietyes, Common-wealths, &amp; ſpecies of Gouernement firſt tooke their originall. For the mantainance of which ſociety, there is no queſtion, but God hath giuen many priuiledges to a Father, as well to reward the well-deſeruing, as to puniſh an euill child, or member of his body: not onely,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16185:27"/>by depriuing them of their expected fortunes; but by cutting them of from his body, either by baniſhment, or by death it ſelfe. For it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the Ciuill law, that a Father had for many yeares, not onely free power to diſinherit, but alſo power of life and death our his children, who ſhould greiuouſly offend him or his, liuing vnder his Ciuill gouernement. But ſince that things vnknowne are growne out of vſe, and may ſeeme as well incredible as ſtraunge: I cannot in diſcretion paſſe ouer the matter in queſtion ſo lightly, as that it may worthily be ſubiect to ſharpe cenſure, or raſhly be branded with the mark of vntruth.</p>
               <p>Therefore laying aſide the teſtimony of the old Roman lawes, in the caſe of a Fathers ſoueraigne power ouer the life of his child, giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him by the lawes of the twelue Tables, where it is written, that<note n="*" place="margin">Leg. <hi>12.</hi> Tabular. cap. <hi>3.</hi> Dionyſ. Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſ. Lib: <hi>2.</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitat.</note> 
                  <hi>Paterfamilias haberetius vitae;</hi> yea more: <hi>ter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> filium venundandi potestatem,</hi> I will briefly, and effectually proue what I affirme herein, out of the ſacred Text it ſelfe. There the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it plainely appeares, that Fathers had power among the Iewes, to cauſe their children for riot, diſorder, or vnthriftines, to be ſtoned to death. <hi>Ergo</hi> power to diſinherit.<note place="margin">Deuter. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> For the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth euer include the leſſe. And not to ſeeme to ſpeake without booke, it ſhall not be amiſſe to ſet downe <hi>Moyſes</hi> words, which are as follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If a man ſhall beget a ſtubborne, and vnruely
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16185:28"/>ſonne, who ſhall not heare the commaundement of his Father, and Mother; and being chastiſed ſhall contemne to obay, they ſhall apprehend and bring him to the ſeniours of that Citty, and to the gate of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And they ſhall ſay to them: This our ſonne is headſtrong, and diſobedient, contemns to heare our admoniſhments, giues himſelfe ouer to rioutous exceſſe, and is a drunkard. The people of that Citty ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme hini with ſtones, and he ſhall dye, that yee may take euill from among you; and that all Iſraell bearing it may feare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of which place in Gods word, wee may gather how odious a vice vnthriftines was among the people of God; &amp; what ample power a Father had to puniſh the ſame in his child. For if wee do well obſerue the manner of the proceſſe, betweene the Father and the child in this caſe, we ſhall fynd that the Father was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, witneſſe, and as it were iudge of his owne cauſe. For we fynd not, that the <hi>Seniours</hi> of the Citty did giue ſentence, or further examyned the proofes of the Fathers accuſation, but their preſence giuing as it were allowance to a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers power, and intention to puniſh his ſonne, the people might without more inquiry, ſtone to death ſo euil a deſeruing child. Which being by my reader well conſidered, my hope is, that it will neuer heerafter ſeeme vnlawfull, though ſomwhat ſtraung, that a Father ſhould diſinherit his eldeſt, or any other ſonne of his, for the cauſe only of vnthriftines.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:16185:28"/>
               <p>And although the world, of men is grown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to that greatnes, that it is neceſſary, that one generall Father, or politique head ſhould be in a Kingdome, or State, which may iuſtly abridge ſome of thoſe priuiledges, and abate a Fathers power; all Fathers being become children to the Father of all Fathers, their Lord and King vnder God: yet the power to raiſe and maintaine a family by good and lawfull means, is ſtill both allowable, and commendable in a Parent. Who may from tyme to tyme reward, according to diſtributiue iuſtice, al thoſe who liue vnder him, by leauing his fortunes to them, as in iuſtice they ſhall deſerue, and law ſhall allow. So that there is no queſtion, but he may ſtill diſinherit, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power of that law vnder which he liues. For no other tye is ouer him; God and Nature allowing that, at this day, and for euer, which once they gaue vnto him. Which autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity he not only may, but ought alſo to execute, as far as the law of man ſhall permit; otherwiſe he ſhal erre in his Paternall iuſtice.</p>
               <p>For a Father is not only to beget and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh his Children in his life, but by Natures law muſt prouide to his power, that they liue both in his life, &amp; after his death to the honour of God the ſeruice of their Country, and Comfort of their family: which were the only ends for which God created man a ciuill &amp; a reaſonable Creature. All which, if it ſhall aſſuredly be thought by a Father, that any Child of his will
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16185:29"/>wholy neglect, or rather execute the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no queſtion, a Father is not bound to leaue him any more then ſhall honeſtly ſuffice the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Nature. For as I haue ſaid before, no man may giue, or lend his goods to any one, who will in all mens iudgments aſſuredly abuſe them.</p>
               <p>But let vs ſee, whether a deſperate vnthrift may be arraigned, and adiuged guilty of theſe accuſations. Surely it is cleere; that all vnthrifty courſes are diſpleaſing to God, and contrary to his honour. And how can he be able to ſerue his Countrey, who in ſhort tyme will not be able to ſerue himſelfe with neceſſaries wherewith to liue, but muſt of force be mainteyned like a Droane in a Common wealth, out of others la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. As for his family, what greater diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort can it haue, then an abſolute ouerthrow: whereby the Noble acts and honour gotten to it by their Predeceſſors vertues, are buried in obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion; and the preſent, and future hopes of all worldly and lawfull honour (vertues temporall rewards) are taken away. And ſhall not all this deſerue diſinheriſon? Can there be a greater ſinne committed againſt the honour, and eſſence of a family, as it is a family, then to be ſpoyled of her honour, &amp; life it ſelf? For in theſe our tymes welgotten goods, and vſed as they ought, are the only ſoule, by which a family, and all the vertuous acts which it hath done, may liue.</p>
               <p>Since therefore the higheſt is ſought and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16185:29"/>aymed at in this ſinne, ſurely according to the proportion of diſtributiue iuſtice, the greateſt puniſhment is in equity due to the ſame, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the reaſon of the precept, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us ſuum vnicui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tribuere.</hi> Nature teartheth the ſilly Bees in their Common wealth, to do to death their <hi>Droanes,</hi> who liue of others labours; and ſhall it then be thought vnlawfull for a Father ſo to puniſh an incorrigible vnthrift, who will not only liue of others labours; but alſo ſubuert the honorable endeauours of his Noble Anceſtors?</p>
               <p>Thus if ſonnes may be deemed &amp; domed by the offended, hauing power to do both, according as the offence done againſt them ſhall by circumſtance be of quality (as we haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued they may and ought;) then certainely it is lawfull for a Father ſo to do, as I haue formerly ſet downe But becauſe example in all doubtfull queſtions, do make their ſide the ſtronger; it ſhal not be amiſſe, for the cleering of all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, to add ſome few to the former, drawne as well from Kinges (by whoſe patterns <hi>totus componitur orbis</hi>) as from inferiour perſons, whoſe qualities beſt fit the condition of our preſent ſubiect. And if kingdomes and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealths haue fauored it, then certainly by all arguments <hi>à maioriad minus,</hi> it may much rather be done, and ought to be ſuffered in priuate families.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:16185:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The maine points of the Premiſſes exemplified in diuers particuler Facts, aſwell of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as of priuate Men.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>t is not fit perhaps to vrge the better acceptance with God, of <hi>Abels</hi> offering aboue <hi>Cayns</hi> the elder Brother, but of that eſtate which <hi>Abel</hi> had in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> Patrimony.<note place="margin">Abel.</note> Nor will I reinforce the memory of <hi>Iaphets</hi> ſhare in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers right to the whole world, though he being the youngeſt ſonne of three, had <hi>Europ</hi> for his inheritance, which in all arts, and vſes of life, far excelleth <hi>Affrick, Aſia,</hi> and all the reſt of the earth. Whereas, according to the pretenſes of thoſe cuſtomary challenges,<note place="margin">Iaphet.</note> 
                  <hi>Sem</hi> ſhould either haue had all, or byn Lord Paramount of all, &amp; <hi>Cham,</hi> and <hi>Iaphet</hi> with their poſterity but Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, or Fre-holders vnder him.</p>
               <p>I will not alſo (as if there were penury of reſemblances) againe vſe for example <hi>Eſaus</hi> diſinheriſion, though that were inough for our preſent purpoſe. For if it had bene ſinne (which <hi>Ioſiphus</hi> the Iew, neither in his Antiquities, or Scripture faith) the Mother could not haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it, God would not haue proſpered it, nor
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16185:30"/>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> himſelfe, being a good man, haue accepted it, nor <hi>Eſau</hi> (whoſe anger <hi>Iacob</hi> feared) haue left it vnreuenged. Neither is there in Scripture, nor in any writen Law vnder heauen, any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to reſtraine the Fathers power, but rather the contrary. For ſuch is the law of Nature that they who are, <hi>exaequo,</hi> one mans children, ſhould, if not <hi>exaequo,</hi> yet not <hi>exini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo,</hi> be prouided for.</p>
               <p>Againſt which partiality, the Imperiall Lawes admit ſo forcible a remedy, vnder the title of an inofficious Teſtament, as it ſhal inable the yonger childe, to a certaine proportion of eſtate, whether the deceaſed Father would or no if he had no iuſt reaſon for omiſſion, or diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uowment in his laſt will. The example certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely of the ſame holy Patriarch <hi>Iacob,</hi> in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Ephraim</hi> before <hi>Manaſſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephraim.</note> the younger ſon before the elder, being his grandchildren, againſt the ſet purpoſe of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> their Father, ſeemes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwerable on behalfe of the power of parents for transferring, or diſtributing their bleſſings. Of which it may truely be ſaid, <hi>Qui prior in bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictione est potior in iure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of <hi>Salomon</hi> I haue ſpoken before, who was not the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Salomon.</note> but <hi>Adonai</hi> after <hi>Abſalom</hi> was ſlaine: as <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe was not the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>leſſe</hi> his Father, but the youngeſt, and yet choſen by God (who ſees not as man doth, for with him there is <hi>reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonarum</hi>) to gouerne <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though he was not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16185:31"/>ſet before his brothers in the priuate inheritance of his familie. And in the Ghoſpell it is apparent by the Parable of the workmen, who came at vnequall houres into the vineyard, and yet had equal wages, that firſt and laſt are to him a like, who though he created thinges in number, weight, and meaſure, yet he ſquares not his fauors by priority of being, but of well-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Augustus Caeſar,</hi> the moſt renowned of all the firſt Emperours, ſetled the ſucceſſion of his Empire, not vpon his onely G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andchilde <hi>Agrippa Poſthumus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Agrippa Poſthumus</note> the ſonne of his daughter &amp; ſole heyre the lady <hi>Iulia,</hi> though <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſayth that he was <hi>nullius ſtagitij comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtus</hi> (then what if he had indeed byn a notorious vnthrift) but vpon <hi>Tiberius</hi> a ſtranger in bloud, and his ſonne by no other, but by a ciuill title of Adoption, becauſe he reputed him far the fitter to gouerne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Choſroas</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Medarſes.</note> made <hi>Medarſes</hi> his younger ſonne companion in his Empire, and left out his eldeſt ſonne <hi>Sinochius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let forraine examples paſſe for briefnes ſake, wherwith of all tymes, &amp; places books are full.</p>
               <p>In our Country wee might alledg the fact of <hi>Brutus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brutus.</note> the reputed fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of our Nation, who diuided <hi>Albion,</hi> afterward called <hi>Brittaine,</hi> to his three ſonnes, leauing onely the beſt por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Locrinus,</hi> ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly called <hi>Loegres; Albania</hi> (now Scotland) to <hi>Albanact;</hi> and <hi>Cambria,</hi> or
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16185:31"/>
                  <hi>Wales</hi> to <hi>Camber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leir,</hi> long after, knew he had ſo much power in himſelfe as a Father, euen againſt the euidence of his owne act of partition, by the originall law of Nature; as for the ingratitude of his owne children, to confer the kingdome wholy vpon his younger child <hi>Cordeilla</hi> in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of his grandſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgan</hi> and <hi>Cunedage,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cordeilla</note> borne of his eldeſt daughters.</p>
               <p>I knowe that ſome will deny credit to <hi>Brutus</hi> hiſtory, which in this caſe they might with the more reaſon do if the ancient Weale, or Brittiſh Cuſtome, did not anſwere in the practiſe thereof, to that act of <hi>Brutus.</hi> For, not onely king <hi>Roderick</hi> deuided his kingdome of <hi>Wales</hi> to his three ſonnes, according to that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the countrey into <hi>Northwales, South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wales,</hi> and <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſland,</hi> but others ſince haue done the like among them.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Brutus</hi> Hiſtory,<note place="margin">Brutus Hiſtory,</note> an it hath ſome enmies ſo alſo hath is many friends, and thoſe of ſpeciall worth and note <hi>Henry</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Huntington, Matthew</hi> of <hi>Weſtminiſter,</hi> &amp; others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ancient. And of later tymes, <hi>Syr Iohn Price, William Lambert, Humphrey Lloyds,</hi> Doctor <hi>White</hi> of <hi>Baſingstoke</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> in right of the Ciuill law Chaire (an honour due to the iuſt number of years by him paſſed) &amp; innumerable others. Aboue all the reſt, <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt King of <hi>England,</hi> with all the Earles &amp; Barons of this Realme, by their authentick deed or inſtrument,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16185:32"/>confirmed in Parliament. But let vs proceed.</p>
               <p>They who know the old faſhions of <hi>Ireland,</hi> either by report, or by the printed Statutes of that Nation, may teſtify of their moſt ancient Tenure,<note place="margin">Iriſh. Tauiſtry.</note> or Fundament cuſtome, which there is called <hi>Tauiſtry.</hi> By which the land and chiefeſt of a Name, after the predeceſſors death, is not a warded to the eldeſt ſonne but to the worthieſt (if I miſremember not) the iudgment wherof is left with the people and ſuch Tenants about as haue intereſt and right of voyce. As <hi>Alexander</hi> the great though (as it is apparent in the Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees) very falſly is ſaid to haue left his Empire. And the cuſtome of equal ſhares may be in other places alſo, which neuer borrowed their equall partitions from <hi>Gauelkind:</hi> A cuſtome, I graunt, which ſome haue very lately altered in their priuate families by Parliament.</p>
               <p>In Scotland, there is ſcarſe any thing in their moſt ancient <hi>Records,</hi> more often found concerning their ſucceſſion to the Crowne ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then Vncles to reigne before Nephewes, euer by Nationall Cuſtome, as is auerred. But the abundance of forraine examples muſt not carry me from home.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Arthur?</note> 
                  <hi>Arthur</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> was left heyre to the crowne by his Father King <hi>Vther,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Pendragon,</hi> or <hi>Dragons head,</hi> though begotten in Baſtardy, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of <hi>Lot</hi> king of <hi>Pic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tland,</hi> being borne of <hi>Vthers</hi> ſiſter or, as ſome write, of his daughter <hi>Anne:</hi> an hiſtory which euen <hi>Buchanan</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:16185:32"/>relateth out of the Scottiſh Monuments, on <hi>Arthurs</hi> behalf, for very true. To come neerer in the ſame kynd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athelſtane,</hi> that victorious king of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Athelſtane</note> being a Baſtard, was notwithſtanding prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before the lawfull eldeſt ſonne, euen by his Father King <hi>Edward,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Sinior,</hi> to whom (ſaith <hi>Florentius Wigornienſs,</hi> an authour aboue 500 yeares old) <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gni gub? rnacula reliquit,</hi> and not to any of his ſonnes by his wife &amp; Queence. Little cauſe is there to ſeeke examples ſo far off. <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerour</hi> preferred <hi>William</hi> his youngeſt ſonne, before <hi>Robert</hi> the eldeſt in the Kingdome of <hi>England:</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt was ſurrogated to <hi>Rufus</hi> his Brother:<note place="margin">VVilliam Rufus.</note> and ſtill kept <hi>Robert</hi> out.</p>
               <p>The title of more ſufficiency, not of more propinquity made <hi>Stephen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">K. Stephen</note> as being then a man growne, to ſtep in before <hi>Matildes</hi> the Empreſſe, and her Infant ſonne <hi>Henry Plantagenet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will not ſpeake of King <hi>Iohns</hi> ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion before his nephew <hi>Arthur,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Gef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> the elder brother to <hi>Iohn. Henry</hi> the 4.<note place="margin">K. Iohn.</note> King of <hi>England,</hi> did in open Parliament pretend a deſcent from <hi>Edmund</hi> Earle of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Edmund Earle of Lancaſter.</note> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of <hi>Henry</hi> the third king of <hi>England,</hi> in preiudice of king <hi>Richard</hi> 2. auering that <hi>Edmund</hi> was diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited for deformity, and his brother <hi>Edward</hi> (afterward by the name of king <hi>Edward</hi> 1.) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. Which, though it were not ſo, yet is it ſufficient to ſhew that <hi>Henry</hi> 4. did hould, that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16185:33"/>his anceſtour king <hi>Henry</hi> 3. might haue done ſuch an act, if the cauſe had bene ſufficient.</p>
               <p>And what intereſt had <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hmoud</hi> to his Diademe, being neyther of the right bloud nor of the Royall Name, when neuertheleſſe of the true: <hi>Plantagenets</hi> ſundry Males were aliue; and one of them at that very tyme king of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> alſo in poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>But to leane Kings affaires. If all muſt neceſſufily haue gone to one, how came it then to paſſe, that in this kingdome there were at one tyme, ſo many great and honorable families of one bloud; diſinyned in their ſeats, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in their Annories by different argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Our whous to meanly ſeeme in our anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities and ſtories, as not to knowe it was ſo? And that many renowned houſes (to ſpeake as <hi>de magis notis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>) <hi>Plantag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sundry grint Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> at a tyme.</note> 
                  <hi>Mortiniers, Beaufords, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>champ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> 1 <hi>Disla-Poles, Neuill, Grayes,</hi> and the like, haue growne and flouriſhed out of one common Anceſtour? It can neuer be refel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               <p>Of diſinheriſions in worthy Families, <hi>M. William Camden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>renceaux</hi> King of Arnies giues vs two eminent examples. And who is he that remembers not one or other, in this owne knowledge, or acquaintance?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ianc,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Hugh Courtney,</hi> and heyre to her Mother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Carewes</note> wife of <hi>Nirold</hi> Lord <hi>Carew,</hi> diſinaerited her eldeſt ſonne <hi>Thomas, cùm mirùs reuerenter matrem haberet;</hi> and parted her lands
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16185:33"/>(which were goodly) among her three younger ſonnes, of whom are ſprung three ſeuerall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull bouſes of the <hi>Carewes,</hi> called <hi>Haccombe, Anthony,</hi> and <hi>Bury.</hi> So that God hath by the ſucceſſe confirmed the lawfulnes of the fact. And this is the firſt of <hi>Maister Caindens</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
               <p>The other is this. <hi>Bryand Lile,</hi> or <hi>Fitz-Earle,</hi> Lord of <hi>Abergeuenny</hi> hauing two ſonnes,<note place="margin">Brientius de inſula.</note> both leprous, built for them a <hi>Lazaretto,</hi> or ſpittall, &amp; gaue to <hi>Miles Earle</hi> of <hi>Hereſord</hi> far the greateſt part of his patrimony from his Children. The one of theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples is in the deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Deuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and this other in <hi>Monmouthſhire.</hi> And this Chapter may ſuffice for the illuſtration, and clearing the former Doctrine, and the ſubiect of this whole diſcourſe by examples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:16185:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> That the Law of Naturall Equity &amp; Reaſon confirme iust Diſinheriſion. &amp; that the rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous liues of Elder Brothers deſerue that vehement reproofe with which the Author cloſeth vp this Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET vs now looke into the Nature of equity, and examine whether in Naturall reaſon, which is the law of all lawes, the temperate ought to be ſubiect to intemperate. Fooles &amp; Madmen, to whom no law imputes ſinne, are not puniſhed for theft, or murther, or for any other offence which they do, being mad, or vnreaſonable. For though humanely they cannot offend: yet in this ſort, according to equity, they many be puniſhed. The reaſon is; That all law being grounded on Naturall equity (for otherwiſe it is no law) doth not only puniſh offences co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted; but alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces which may be done, by reaſonable or vnreaſonable creatures. And ſince that Fooles and Madmen cannot offend to be puniſhed, or by puniſhment can be reformed; and yet they with whom they ſhall liue, ſhall ſurely be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16185:34"/>if not ouerthrowne by them hauing power, as Namely Brothers, Siſters, and all their whole family put in daunger of miſery and ruine: the law, <hi>according to all Natural equity</hi> takes al power from them.</p>
               <p>I haue inſerted this clauſe <hi>according to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall equity,</hi> for that it is againſt Nature, that men ſhould be ſubiect to beaſts, or inſenſible creatures. Heerupon <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> diſputing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of rule and ſubiection, ſaith: That none are borne ſlaues, but ſuch as Nature hath abridged of the vſe of reaſon, who being truly ſlaues, are altogether vnfit to gouerne. Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ground alſo the ſame great Philoſopher; diſputing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Monarchy or Comonweale is the better forme of Policy; he ſaith, a Comonweale: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the wiſeſt &amp; beſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are admitted to ſway therein.</p>
               <p>But, it may be ſaid, What is all this to our purpoſe? Yes; thus far it may be well applied. If Nature, intent to make al mankind reaſonable according to their <hi>ſpecies,</hi> being hindered by ſome ineuitable accident, ſhall ſo blemiſh and maime thoſe, in whom ſuch want, and Natural weaknes ſhalbe found, that they, according to diuine, and humane law, may and ought to be depriued of all right and clayme to any thing more then to ſuſtaine Nature; as other creatures may do, and not to giue vnto them any ſouerai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnty, rule, or gouernement, which by law, or cuſtome might otherwiſe haue falne on them:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16185:35"/>Becauſe, according to naturall &amp; diuine equity, neither man, nor yet the creature made for mans vſe, ought to be gouerned by Beaſtes: and ſuch do fooles and madmen ſeeme.</p>
               <p>If this be ſo (as according to Natures rule it cannot be otherwiſe) what puniſhment ſhall we think due to that reaſonable creature, borne in a ciuill ſociety of men, vnto whom Nature hath not bene a Stepdame in beſtowing of her bleſſings; &amp; whoſe name and Family hath bene ennobled, and enriched by the induſtry and vertue of many worthy Predeceſſors, who ſhall through diſorder, and inordinate deſires, habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated in him by cuſtome &amp; euill conuerſation, become vnreaſonable, yea a ſinfull-creature a wilfull, and moſt puniſhable madman, and a thing vnworthy the name of man, a <hi>Prodigall;</hi> who contrary to all rule law, or order of the moſt barbarous ſociety of men, takes away the ſoule (as I haue ſaid before) of all his <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> who being dead, yet long might liue in their poſterity; and conſumes the womb (his family I meane) wherein he was borne: and without all remembrance of his obligation to the dead, (whom as hauing his being from them, he ought to honour) or reſpect to the huing (to whome he ſhould be a comfort) deuoures in ſome ſort, them of his owne <hi>ſpecies,</hi> ſociety, and bloud. All which the <hi>Anthropophages</hi> do not.</p>
               <p>For though they feed on their <hi>ſpecies,</hi> which are men like to themſelues; yet they hunt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16185:35"/>after ſtraungers, and nouriſh then neareſt bloud with others fleſh, obſeruing ſtill ſome law of ſociety among themſelues, which our ciuill monſter doth not. For he, contrary to all courſe of Nature ſucks out oftentimes the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oud of his neareſt, and deareſt friends; namely his children, brothers, and ſiſters:<note place="margin">Ariotous heyre is a ciuill Monſter.</note> yea ſome haue brought their all-tender-harted parents to the greateſt of all woes, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ary in, their old age:</hi> And all this to maintaine by force, of fraud, a damned crew of Diuells in the shapes of men.</p>
               <p>Nature hath giuen, yea ſhe ſo ſtrongly hath inhabituated a laudable deſire in all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to preſerue them <hi>ſpecies,</hi> that directly, or in directly, to vndergo the contrary, wore not onely vnnatural and mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rous, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>worthy alſo of ſeuereſt puniſhment, Families, let them be Princely, Noble, Gentle or Vulgar, are in a manner particuler kindes; or <hi>ſpecies</hi> allowed of by Natures law to be raiſed; or maintaine of, vnder, or in their cheife <hi>genus,</hi> mankind vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall: which to ouerthrow either directly, or indirectly, let the Philoſopher either Naturall, or Morall: the Lawier either Ciull or Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>; the Diuine, Scholeman, or Caſuiſt, iudge how puniſhable.</p>
               <p>Morall Law-makers for many ages, pretermitted to make lawes, againſt this ſort of oftenders: being asked why? they anſweared: That no man could be ſo ingratefull or inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:16185:36"/>
               <p>By which wee ſee how grieuous the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was deemed by them, and how ſeuere puniſhment (were they to make lawes in theſe our corrupted times) they would preſcribe for ſuch offenders. Thus much for our preſent matter in queſtion. In the arguing whereof, if what I write in defence of younger Brothers, as here the caſe is put, I ſeem to haue taken vpon truſt, rather then vpon knowledge, or reading: the wiſer ſort will (I hope) not blame me. For my intent was nor, but onely as at firſt I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, to ſet downe a Table-diſcourſe, and not a Controuerſy diſcuſſed in Schooles.</p>
               <p>If I haue ſpoken according to dialecticall reaſon as I belieue) then may I ſafely think; that my diſcourſe is armed with ſtrong Authority. For what hath bene ſpoken heretofore truely, which reaſon hath not dictated to all Authors pens? If therefore I were able to cite a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand great Writers for what I haue ſaid; yet ſhould they be no more, but that which Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon hath, or may teach daily. All which, with my ſelf, I intruſt to the gentle and equall Cenſure of my Courtuous Reader.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:16185:36"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
